<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-03T17:49:36+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Anna E. Kijas</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rebalancing the Music Canon</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/rebalancing-the-music-canon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rebalancing the Music Canon"/><published>2019-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/rebalancing-music-canon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/rebalancing-the-music-canon/"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to share news about a <a href="https://rebalancing-music-canon.com">project</a> that I have been thinking about starting since I gave my <a href="https://medium.com/@kijas/https-medium-com-kijas-what-does-the-data-tell-us-926ba830702f">keynote</a> about the lack of women and people of color in digital music/data projects at the Music Encoding Conference in May 2018 at University of Maryland. I wanted to create a music data repository focused on works by un(der)-represented people with the aim of decentering the musical canon and making data-driven music scholarship more diverse and inclusive. In particular, the repository will contain a dataset of compositions spanning a large historical period by an un(der)-represented group (primarily women and people of color) that has generally been left out of (big) data driven scholarship work.</p> <p>There are a number of resources out there that can aid in the creation of this repository, one in particular stood out to me as a good candidate for the first corpus. I reached out to Molly Murdock (Eastman School of Music) and Ben Parsell (St. Olaf College) of <a href="https://musictheoryexamplesbywomen.com/contributors/">Music Theory Examples by Women</a> and discussed my idea of encoding a small corpus of works by women, what the benefits of this would be, and how the data could be used by other scholars, students, and researchers for a variety of purposes, including rendering the scores from <a href="https://music-encoding.org/">MEI</a> to HTML using a tool called <a href="https://www.verovio.org/index.xhtml">Verovio</a>.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/musictheoryexamples.png" width="400px" style="float:right;padding-left:25px" alt="screenshot of Music Theory Examples by Women website" title="screenshot of Music Theory Examples by Women website"/></p> <p>This appealed to them so I got to work by training two of our Boston College Libraries Digital Studio students (Nicolas Sucre and Alben Chingo) over the summer of 2018. They tested a workflow that I put together (currently an internal manual) that provided guidance on how to extract, correct, and encode data from this initial corpus. The testing and workflow has developed into an upcoming publication with <a href="https://mith.umd.edu/people/person/raffaele-viglianti/">Raffaele Viglianti</a> (MITH) for the <a href="https://www.diglib.org/dlfteach-digital-library-pedagogy-cookbook/">DLF Digital Library Pedagogy Cookbook</a>, which will be shared widely once it is published online.</p> <p>The music data repository for <a href="https://github.com/annakijas1/rebalancing-music-canon/">Rebalancing the Music Canon: Collaborative Music Encoding project</a> is now available online. In this repository we will keep the extracted, corrected, and encoded data. You can also <a href="https://rebalancing-music-canon.com/">visit the project website</a> to read more about the process, corpus 1, how to contribute, and the collaborators. We hope to have additional collaborators joining us soon. If you are interested in contributing to this project in any way, please feel free to contact me directly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’d like to share news about a project that I have been thinking about starting since I gave my keynote about the lack of women and people of color in digital music/data projects at the Music Encoding Conference in May 2018 at University of Maryland. I wanted to create a music data repository focused on works by un(der)-represented people with the aim of decentering the musical canon and making data-driven music scholarship more diverse and inclusive. In particular, the repository will contain a dataset of compositions spanning a large historical period by an un(der)-represented group (primarily women and people of color) that has generally been left out of (big) data driven scholarship work.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why is it so quiet here?</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/why-is-it-so-quiet-here/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is it so quiet here?"/><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/why-is-it-so-quiet-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/why-is-it-so-quiet-here/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20221201033128/https://www.annakijas.com/why-is-it-so-quiet-here/">http://web.archive.org/web/20221201033128/https://www.annakijas.com/why-is-it-so-quiet-here/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: http://web.archive.org/web/20221201033128/https://www.annakijas.com/why-is-it-so-quiet-here/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Libraries and museums are essential contributors to Americans’ lives</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/libraries-and-museums-are-essential-contributors-to-americans-lives/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Libraries and museums are essential contributors to Americans’ lives"/><published>2017-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/libraries-and-museums-are-essential-contributors-to-americans-lives</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/libraries-and-museums-are-essential-contributors-to-americans-lives/"><![CDATA[<p>In the President’s <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/BUDGET-2018-BLUEPRINT/pdf/BUDGET-2018-BLUEPRINT.pdf">proposed FY 2018 budget</a> (p. 5), the <a href="https://www.imls.gov/">Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS)</a> is one of eighteen independent agencies that would be completely eliminated. In a <a href="https://www.imls.gov/news-events/news-releases/institute-museum-and-library-services-issues-statement-presidents-proposed">statement</a> from the Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services, Dr. Katheryn K. Matthew describes the value and impact that funding from the IMLS has on communities:</p> <p>“The institutions we serve provide vital resources that contribute significantly to Americans’ economic development, education, health, and well-being… our grants and programs support libraries and museums as essential contributors to improving Americans’ quality of life.”</p> <p>A long list of professional organizations have spoken out against the proposed cuts to the NEA, NEH, and IMLS; and many of these organizations and individuals are urging people to contact their representatives in order to demonstrate the impact that the programs funded by these agencies have made on our lives, society, and cultural existence.<sup><a href="#fn1">1</a></sup></p> <p>What impact does the IMLS have on people, who are not librarians, curators, archivists, etc., and their communities across the United States? The IMLS was founded 20 years ago and its primary mission is to provide federal support to approximately 120,000 libraries and <a href="http://museumstat.org/">30,000 museums</a> in the United States and its territories. IMLS grants range from small amounts of $715 that funded for example, the <a href="http://www.opusarchives.org/">OPUS Archives and Research Center</a> in their efforts to preserve and store 16mm film reels from their <a href="http://www.opusarchives.org/joseph-campbell-collection/">Joseph Campbell Collection</a>, to large, institution building grants of $10,000,000 that funded the National Constitution Center (FY 1999), whose <a href="https://constitutioncenter.org/about/mission-history">mission</a> is to “illuminate constitutional ideals and inspire active citizenship.” The Center was established in 1988 when President Ronald Reagan signed the <a href="http://www.heritage.org/political-process/report/constitutional-president-ronald-reagan-and-the-founding">Constitution Heritage Act of 1988</a> in order to create a center that “shall disseminate information about the United States Constitution on a nonpartisan basis in order to increase awareness and understanding of the Constitution among the American people.”</p> <p>Of the 13,594 IMLS grants awarded between FY 1996 and 2014 – 4,046 were awarded for the <a href="https://www.imls.gov/grants/available/native-american-library-services-basic-grants">Native American Library Services</a>, <a href="https://www.imls.gov/grants/available/native-americannative-hawaiian-museum-services-program">Native American/Native Hawaiian Museum Services</a> or <a href="https://www.imls.gov/grants/available/native-hawaiian-library-services">Native Hawaiian Library Services</a> programs, which serve communities who are federally recognized <a href="https://www.imls.gov/node/35/">as an “Indian tribe” or “Native Hawaiian”</a> for the latter. The Native American Library Services and Native Hawaiian Library Services programs provide critical funding for library staff to continue their education and training and participate in professional development. The Native American/Native Hawaiian Museum Services program enables organizations to develop public programming and educational services, as well as provide ongoing professional development for their staff.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/anna.kijas#!/vizhome/IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014/IMLSGrants1996-2014"><img class="wp-image-749 size-medium" src="http://www.annakijas.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Screen-Shot-2017-03-23-at-10.51.58-PM-300x215.png" alt="Alaska - select grants" width="400" height="325"/></a> </div> <p>Figure 1. IMLS grant funding under the Native American Library Services program in Alaska.</p> <p>In remote areas of the United States, such as Alaska, IMLS grants for programs and existing library operations and core services can be an essential source of funding. States, such as Ohio, also rely heavily on funding from the IMLS for programs and services, such as the <a href="https://library.ohio.gov/news/state-library-ohio-statement-impact-presidents-proposed-elimination-institute-museum-library-services/">Ohio Talking Book program</a> for the blind and physically disabled population, which without IMLS funding would be difficult to support or could even be forced to end.</p> <p>Additional information about programs and services that have received IMLS grants can be searched and viewed in the <a href="https://www.imls.gov/grants/awarded-grants">IMLS database</a>. Open data about IMLS grant recipients is also available on <a href="https://www.data.gov/">data.gov</a>. I used this source to pull data and <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/anna.kijas#!/vizhome/IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014/IMLSGrants1996-2014">visualize it using Tableau Public</a>. Filters enable you to select and view data on the map based on values such as fiscal year, total amount awarded, state (or territory), institution, organization type, program, and project type. The organization type is color coded and the size of the points correlates to the amount awarded to a specific project. The goal of this visualization is to show that IMLS grants impact many communities across the United States and its Territories and to encourage people to learn more about the programs and services in their towns and cities funded through IMLS, which they might not realize they benefit from in some way.</p> <p>Open interactive map by visiting <a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/anna.kijas#!/vizhome/IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014/IMLSGrants1996-2014">this page</a>.</p> <div id="viz1490326278510" class="tableauPlaceholder" style="position: relative;"><noscript>&amp;lt;a href='#'&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img alt='IMLS Grants (1996-2014) ' src='https:&amp;amp;#47;&amp;amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;amp;#47;static&amp;amp;#47;images&amp;amp;#47;IM&amp;amp;#47;IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014&amp;amp;#47;IMLSGrants1996-2014&amp;amp;#47;1_rss.png' style='border: none' /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;</noscript><object class="tableauViz" style="display: none;" width="750" height="700"><param name="host_url" value="https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F"/> <param name="site_root" value=""/><param name="name" value="IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014/IMLSGrants1996-2014"/><param name="tabs" value="no"/><param name="static_image" value="https://public.tableau.com/static/images/IM/IMLSDiscretionaryGrantFunding1996-2014/IMLSGrants1996-2014/1.png"/> <param name="animate_transition" value="yes"/><param name="display_static_image" value="yes"/><param name="display_spinner" value="yes"/><param name="display_overlay" value="yes"/><param name="display_count" value="yes"/></object></div> <script type="text/javascript">var divElement=document.getElementById("viz1490326278510"),vizElement=divElement.getElementsByTagName("object")[0];vizElement.style.width="100%",vizElement.style.height=.75*divElement.offsetWidth+"px";var scriptElement=document.createElement("script");scriptElement.src="https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js",vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement,vizElement);</script> <p> </p> <p> </p> <hr/> <p><sup id="fn1">1. In <a href="http://www.infodocket.com/2017/03/16/trumps-federal-budget-proposal-eliminates-funding-for-imls-nea-neh-cpb-and-more/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Trump’s Budget Proposal Eliminates Funding For IMLS, NEA, NEH, CPB, and More,” </a>INFOdocket, Library Journal. (March 16, 2017), Gary Price compiled and published excerpts and a running list of statements from professional organizations in response to the President’s proposal to eliminate funding for these agencies. There are other statements that didn’t make it into the list, for example, the <a href="https://www.musiclibraryassoc.org/forums/Posts.aspx?topic=1344902" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Music Library Association Statement on Proposed Cuts to Arts and Humanities</a>. (March 21, 2017).<a title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text." href="#ref1">↩</a></sup></p> <p> </p> <p> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the President’s proposed FY 2018 budget (p. 5), the Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS) is one of eighteen independent agencies that would be completely eliminated. In a statement from the Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services, Dr. Katheryn K. Matthew describes the value and impact that funding from the IMLS has on communities:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy 163rd Birthday, Teresa Carreño / Feliz Cumpleaños!</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/693/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy 163rd Birthday, Teresa Carreño / Feliz Cumpleaños!"/><published>2016-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/693</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/693/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is avaiable in the Wayback Machine: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/693/">http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/693/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is avaiable in the Wayback Machine: http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/693/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Post-Election Statements Data Set</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/post-election-statements-data-set/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post-Election Statements Data Set"/><published>2016-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/post-election-statements-data-set</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/post-election-statements-data-set/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161129155553/http://www.annakijas.com/post-election-statements-data-set/">https://web.archive.org/web/20161129155553/http://www.annakijas.com/post-election-statements-data-set/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: https://web.archive.org/web/20161129155553/http://www.annakijas.com/post-election-statements-data-set/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MLA Conference Diary (Reflection on Challenges, Evolving Roles, and Community)</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/mla-conference-diary-reflection-on-challenges-evolving-roles-and-community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MLA Conference Diary (Reflection on Challenges, Evolving Roles, and Community)"/><published>2016-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/mla-conference-diary-reflection-on-challenges-evolving-roles-and-community</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/mla-conference-diary-reflection-on-challenges-evolving-roles-and-community/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Cross-posted on the <a href="MLA Conference Diary">http://www.iaml.info/news/mla-conference-diary-2-0</a> (IAML website).</em> The annual conference of the Music Library Association was held March 2-5, 2016 in Cincinnati, Ohio.</p> <p>Each year the MLA conference brings together people with a shared interest in music librarianship and music resources. While this interest may be directly linked to our professional roles and careers, we also represent a community of people who may have started out as musicians, archivists and librarians working with music-specific materials, but now represent roles in emerging or evolving areas, such as metadata, discovery services, digital preservation, or digital humanities. It is this sense of community that brings me (and others I know) to the MLA conference every year.</p> <p>At this year’s conference, I especially enjoyed attending sessions that challenge how we think about our profession, organization and its membership, such as our opening plenary <a href="&quot;Diversity in MLA">http://www.musiclibraryassoc.org/mpage/mla_2016_abs_1_1PC</a>,” in which panelists explored and discussed approaches for recruiting a diverse membership, as well as supporting librarians from underrepresented groups through programs, such as the <a href="ARL/MLA Diversity &amp; Inclusion Initiative">http://www.arl.org/leadership-recruitment/diversity-recruitment/arl-mla-diversity-inclusion-initiative#.VuLZ4JMrJTY</a>. There were many sessions on the program, which inspire and challenge us to continue learning, growing, and collaborating as a community, however I’ll only mention a few, including the plenary <a href="&quot;Practical Application of Linked Data,”">http://www.musiclibraryassoc.org/mpage/mla_2016_abs_2_1PC</a> [http://www.musiclibraryassoc.org/mpage/mla_2016_abs_2_3PC] (“Bridging Emerging and Established Approaches to Music Research”) panel, and the <a href="&quot;Approaches to Digital Scholarship: Hands-on Workshop Series&quot;.">http://www.musiclibraryassoc.org/mpage/mla_2016_abs_3_2BC</a></p> <p>The session on linked data and series on digital scholarship are especially close to my own work at this point in my career and it is very inspiring to see the excitement shown by colleagues when discussing approaches, projects, topics and concepts that continue to challenge those in and outside our profession. It is through presentations on projects, such as <a href="Linked Jazz">https://linkedjazz.org/</a> or the <a href="Hip Hop Collection">http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/hiphop/</a>, as well as through teaching practical applications of concepts, such as linked data, digital curation, or (meta)data visualization, in a hands-on learning environment, that we demonstrate the value for and actual application of these concepts and methods that may otherwise seem abstract to many. The session on emerging and established approaches to music research raised questions about how we teach students (future scholars/librarians) how to do research, as well as how to use digital tools and methods from areas such as digital humanities, in order to move their discipline forward. Questions were raised around what it means to be an expert in one’s field vs. someone who applies discipline-specific methodology or (digital) tools without fully understanding the underlying principles or theories, as well as whose perspective is valued and why?</p> <p>Despite my own professional move outside of music librarianship, conversations and sessions on topics, such as the ones above, encourage and reaffirm my decision to continue participating in and attending the annual MLA conference; and I hope that they will likewise inspire library students, new professionals, and those outside the MLA whose interests, skills, and roles intersect with music in some way, but do not stop there.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cross-posted on the http://www.iaml.info/news/mla-conference-diary-2-0 (IAML website). The annual conference of the Music Library Association was held March 2-5, 2016 in Cincinnati, Ohio.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where are the Women (Inductees) at the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame?</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/where-are-the-women-inductees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where are the Women (Inductees) at the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame?"/><published>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/where-are-the-women-inductees</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/where-are-the-women-inductees/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20160811120152/http://www.annakijas.com/where-are-the-women-inductees/">http://web.archive.org/web/20160811120152/http://www.annakijas.com/where-are-the-women-inductees/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: http://web.archive.org/web/20160811120152/http://www.annakijas.com/where-are-the-women-inductees/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Madeleines and Breadcrumbs, Discovering the Musical Past through Multimodal Analyses</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Madeleines and Breadcrumbs, Discovering the Musical Past through Multimodal Analyses"/><published>2015-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses/">http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/digital-madeleines-and-breadcrumbs-discovering-the-musical-past-through-multimodal-analyses/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making the metadata work for you</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/making-the-metadata-work-for-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making the metadata work for you"/><published>2015-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/making-the-metadata-work-for-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/making-the-metadata-work-for-you/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220626235027/https://www.annakijas.com/making-the-metadata-work-for-you/">https://web.archive.org/web/20220626235027/https://www.annakijas.com/making-the-metadata-work-for-you/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: https://web.archive.org/web/20220626235027/https://www.annakijas.com/making-the-metadata-work-for-you/.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adventures in Geocoding for Neatline</title><link href="https://annakijas1.github.io/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adventures in Geocoding for Neatline"/><published>2014-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annakijas1.github.io/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annakijas1.github.io/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline/">http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline/</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is available in the Wayback Machine: http://web.archive.org/web/20220522034325/https://www.annakijas.com/adventures-in-geocoding-for-neatline/.]]></summary></entry></feed>