<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-09-23T10:11:07+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andy Wenk</title><subtitle>Personal website of Andy Wenk - Hamburg, Germany
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Irreducible Components of Leadership</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2016/the-irreducible-components-of-leadership/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Irreducible Components of Leadership" /><published>2016-11-01T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-01T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2016/the-irreducible-components-of-leadership</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2016/the-irreducible-components-of-leadership/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="paul-oneill-the-irreducible-components-of-leadership">Paul O’Neill The Irreducible Components of Leadership</h1>

<p>During a discussion regarding the Hamburg based company JIMDO and them firing 75 awesome people, I was pointed to this awesome talk by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_H._O%27Neill">Paul O’Neill</a> about leadership (Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/s0enke">@s0enke</a>). Following you can find my notes I took, while I watched the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=htLCVqaLBvo">video</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A true leader has to articulate non arguable goals</li>
  <li>Finance should not be an objective but a consequence of excellence
<em>In an organisation that has the ‘potential’ for greatness, the people in the organisation can say every day without reservation or hesitation *yes</em> to these three questions:</li>
  <li>I am treated every day with dignity and respect by everyone I encounter, without respect to my gender or my nationality or my race or my educational attainment or my rank or any other discrimination disqualifier.</li>
  <li>I am given the things I need - training, education, tools, encouragement - so that I can make a contribution that gives meaning to my life.</li>
  <li>Every day I can say someone I care about and respect, noticed I did it.</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s the leaders job (and it cannot be delegated to HR) to establish the conditions on an ongoing basis so every person in the institution everyday can say yes to these three propositions. These are goals and cultural characteristics.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Leadership is not writings on the wall, it’s about acting in a noticeable way on the principles you establish, so that people begin to believe that they are real.</li>
  <li>We have to keep things personal, not statistical.</li>
  <li>You get close to zero (in errors, injuries, failures) by continuous learning and continuous improvement from everything going wrong.</li>
  <li>A leader needs to provide running room for people to work to the theoretical limit.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="WorkLife" /><category term="leadership" /><category term="company-culture" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From a talk Paul O'Neill held]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emily Erdbeer R.I.P</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/emily-erdbeer-rip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emily Erdbeer R.I.P" /><published>2015-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/emily-erdbeer-rip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/emily-erdbeer-rip/"><![CDATA[<p><em>So little and cute</em></p>

<p><em>So cheeky and freaky</em></p>

<p><em>So strong and marked</em></p>

<p><br />
I miss you!
<br /></p>

<p><em>So curious and hilarious</em></p>

<p><em>So fast and brave</em></p>

<p><em>So smart and gorgeous</em></p>

<p><br />
We miss you!
<br /></p>

<p>Nature can hurt so much. I believe you will find your peace and say hello to Duke Skelington in heaven …</p>

<p><img src="https://www.andy-wenk.de/assets/img/emily.jpg" alt="Emily Erdbeer" /></p>

<p>∗ September 2003 - † 14.12.2015</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So little and cute]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protest: gegen den Tag der deutschen Patrioten in Hamburg</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/protest-gegen-den-tag-der-deutschen-patrioten-in-hamburg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protest: gegen den Tag der deutschen Patrioten in Hamburg" /><published>2015-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/protest-gegen-den-tag-der-deutschen-patrioten-in-hamburg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/protest-gegen-den-tag-der-deutschen-patrioten-in-hamburg/"><![CDATA[<p>(German only this time … sry)</p>

<p>Die aktuellen Geschehnisse in Deutschland und ganz Europa sind dramatisch. Der Zustrom der Flüchtlinge aus vom Krieg
gebeutelten Ländern wie Syrien, Eritrea, Afghanistan, Irak oder Serbien (<a href="http://www.daserste.de/information/politik-weltgeschehen/mittagsmagazin/sendung/2014/woher-kommen-die-fluechtlinge-in-deutschland-100.html">Quelle</a>) nehmen hitorische Ausmaße an. Den Menschen muss geholfen werden und es liegt in unserer Verantwortung dafür zu sorgen,
dass sie hier in Deutschland willkommen geheissen werden. Natürlich ist auch klar, dass ein Asylantrag geprüft werden muss.</p>

<p>Leider gibt es Menschen in Deutschland, die das anders sehen. Der Rechte Mob hetzt mit Parolen gegen Asylbewerber und
und “Ausländer”. Gegen diese Menschen und deren Einstellung müssen wir uns wehren. Mit gutem Beispiel geht der DGB Hamburg
voran und ruft zur <a href="http://hamburg.dgb.de/themen/++co++3e822116-36b3-11e5-82ba-52540023ef1a">“Demonstration gegen den Naziaufmarsch”</a> auf.</p>

<p>Weitere Informationen sind auch auf der Website <a href="http://www.keine-stimme-den-nazis.org/">“Keine Stimme den Nazis”</a> zu finden.</p>

<p>In diesem Sinne - tut was - wehrt Euch!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.keine-stimme-den-nazis.org" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.keine-stimme-den-nazis.org/images//logo_kein_platz_rgb.jpg" border="0" alt="" width="250" height="204" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="politic" /><category term="hamburg" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aufruf gegen den Tag der deutschen Patrioten am 12.09.2015 in Hamburg]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Darknet - how to deal with todays world wide web</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/the-darknet-how-to-deal-with-todays-world-wide-web/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Darknet - how to deal with todays world wide web" /><published>2015-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/the-darknet---how-to-deal-with-todays-world-wide-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2015/the-darknet-how-to-deal-with-todays-world-wide-web/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently finished reading the book <a href="//www.amazon.de/dp/0434023175/ref=cm_sw_r_tw_dp_pIUivb03J4ERV"><em>The Dark Net</em></a> by Jamie Bartlett. And now I am a bit confused. Read why …</p>

<h2>The book</h2>

<p>I am not going to write a review about the book, because it is not the intention for this post. You can find various <a href="http://goo.gl/t2CJgX">reviews</a> with a bit of googling.</p>

<p>Basically, Bartlett is writing about 4chan, doxxing and trolling, fascist people using the web, silkroad, childporn, porn in general, suicide and eating disorder forums and other “dark sides” of the world wide web. Reading the book is often very disturbing but also eye opening.</p>

<p>I have to admit that I kind of disliked the huge chapter about <em>silk road</em> (a website where you can buy drugs online). I not only had the feeling that Bartlett was impressed by the webiste and it’s customer service, but also seems to be a proponent of sites like <em>silk road</em>. I would not say it is a bad thing in general (he stated some points like shrinking procurement crime) but it needs a very broad disussion to find a point of view.</p>

<h2>Demanding the free world wide web</h2>

<p>Many of us are depressed what authorities know about us, when we surf the www. And a lot of us are against data mining and spying. At least we do not accept, that state authorities are collecting data from everyone just to make sure to not miss any conversations, phonecalls or metadata from potential terrorists. But some of us are going even further and are strictly against any data mining or spying in any way. We demand a free world wide web. Freedom for privacy. I am one of these people.</p>

<p>To make sure that nobody is able to collect our data when surfing the web, we have some possibilities. For communication between two peers, we can encrypt our data. For example by using <a href="https://www.gnupg.org/">GnuPG</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S/MIME">S/Mime</a>. When surfing the Web, we can use the <a href="https://www.torproject.org/about/overview.html.en">Tor-Network</a> and its <a href="https://www.torproject.org/projects/torbrowser.html.en">Tor-Browser</a>. These techniques help to hide our data while communicating or surfing the web.</p>

<h2>The confusion</h2>

<p>But there is a big drawback with all these techniques and our call to the authorities in stopping to spy anyone at all. “The other side” does know these tools also very well.</p>

<p>If you come to the silly conclusion to buy drugs online at silk road, you can do this only when using the Tor-Network by using the Tor-Browser. You have to provide some registration information for sure. To make sure that no one will be able to follow the way back to you, all your trails are blurred. It’s your descision if you want to take the risk. I hope you will not do! (Btw - you will need to priovide a rwal address where the drugs will be sent to … wtf?).</p>

<p>On the other hand, if you want to find some child porn images you have to use the same techniques to hide your data. The administrators of child-porn forums have only one thing in mind: securing the site and resources from the authorities. It is your descision if you want to search for these ressources but it is my descision, that this is in no way acceptable. Never ever!</p>

<p>So here we have a problem. On one side we are able to use the techniques to hide our data from authorities spying us. Ok. Then we can use these techniques for example to harm ourselves by buying drugs and killing us in the end. But there is also the big problem, that ill people with commonly inacceptable sexual orientation are using these techniques to follow their illness.</p>

<p>I don’t want to forget mentioning, that also the ill minded soldiers from the selfcalled <a href="Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant">ISIL</a> and many other terrorist groups are organising themselves with the help of the above mentioned techniques.</p>

<h2>The question</h2>

<p>I ask myself how this should be handled. On one hand, we want to keep our data private. On the other hand we don’t want to accept annonymous abusement of people (especially women) in the world wide web. We don’t want to accept child pronography ressources in the www. We don’t want terrorist to be able to hide themselfs in the depth of the www by encrypting their communication. How can we make sure, that <em>they</em> are not able to use the techniques. This is a very tough question and the answer is most likely “we can’t”.</p>

<p>Child pornography was shrinking until the world wide web was growing fastly at the end of the 90’s in the last century. Now it is almost impossible to fight against these ill people. And let’s not forget, that selling this material is also a market now. Sex sells. In any absurd way.</p>

<h2>My take on this</h2>

<p>I have two little children. They are 5 and 8 years old. They know how to use a tablet, a smartphone and the laptop. They ask us to open pages like <a href="http://www.disney.de/">http://www.disney.de/</a> or <a href="http://www.toggo.de/">http://www.toggo.de/</a>. Wow. It’s unbeliveable how this changed so much compared to when I was a kid.</p>

<p>The world wide web is not the peaceful place we think it is. When I think about my participation in the <a href="http://couchdb.apache.org">Apache CouchDB</a> project and the community we have there, I am very lucky. But we have to discuss a lot of issues in the Open Source world in general. Especially women are a target for abusement in the tech scene. Unfortunately.</p>

<p>The world wide web has a dark side. A very dark side. It fears me a lot and I am very concerned about how my children will participate in this www. I am looking for ways to protect them from all dark sides (it’s still a bit early though). But this is tough.</p>

<p>I am not sure what the best way is with regulation compared to a completely free world wide web. The dark sides are very dark and I think it is not acceptable and tolerable in many situations. So I think we need not only guidelines but also … something else.</p>

<h2>Request for comments</h2>

<p>What are your thoughts on this? Do you know about the <em>dark net</em>? What are your thoughts about regulating the world wide web. Write me an email to andy@nms.de …</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading" /><category term="internet" /><category term="www" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts about the world wide web after reading Jamie Bartlett's book The Dark Net]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CouchDB Weekly News</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/couchdb-weekly-news/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CouchDB Weekly News" /><published>2014-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/couchdb-weekly-news</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/couchdb-weekly-news/"><![CDATA[<p>Up from <a href="http://blog.couchdb.org/2014/03/">March 2014</a>, we started to release the “CouchDB Weekly News”. The reader will find all the interesting news about the development, community affairs, releases and much more of CouchDB and its community. It is an extremely helpful tool to spread the word about CouchDB. What we can say is, that the news are very well received and help the project to be more visible in the world.</p>

<p>The work of aggregating all interesting stuff is done by awesome <a href="https://twitter.com/lrnrd">Lena</a>. She is supported by the <a href="http://couchdb.apache.org/#mailing-lists">Marketing Team</a> and the whole community. Thanks so much Lena for this awesome job.</p>

<p>We are always looking for contributors. If you are especially interested in communiyt-marketing stuff, please subscribe to the <a href="mailto:marketing-subscribe@couchdb.apache.org">marketing mailing-list</a> and drop us a note.</p>

<p>And last, but not least: here are <a href="http://blog.couchdb.org/2014/12/11/couchdb-weekly-news-december-11-2014/">the latest CouchDB News</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><category term="couchdb" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Up from March 2014, we started to release the “CouchDB Weekly News”. The reader will find all the interesting news about the development, community affairs, releases and much more of CouchDB and its community. It is an extremely helpful tool to spread the word about CouchDB. What we can say is, that the news are very well received and help the project to be more visible in the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Screencast with Voila and convert videos for web</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/screencast-with-voila-and-convert-videos-for-web/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Screencast with Voila and convert videos for web" /><published>2014-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/screencast-with-voila-and-convert-videos-for-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/screencast-with-voila-and-convert-videos-for-web/"><![CDATA[<p>I am creating the new version of the website for a elemntary school in Hamburg called <a href="http://preview.schule-neugraben.de/">Grundschule NeugrabenOffene Ganztagsgrundschule (GBS)</a>. The responsible person for the website at this school is a teacher called Steffi and quite ok on working with websoftware. The CMS I am using here is <a href="http://refinerycms.com/">Refinery CMS</a>.</p>

<p>So to make the live easy for Steffi, I decided to create very small screencasts. Well, which one to choose here. As alwasy I need simple software with good results. RTFM is boring so it has to be intuitive.</p>

<p>The search results at Google told me to check out <a href="http://www.globaldelight.com/voila/">Voila</a>. It is available through Apple’s AppStore and has a price of 14.99$ at the moment. So I bought it.</p>

<p>The software is dead simple and the results of the screencasts are very good not say of very high quality. BTW: I am using a Speedlink Medusa NX headset with microphone (I have that for my job when I work form home for video-web-talks). After creating a screencast you are able to upload the screencast to Google Drive, Vimeo and others. So I uploaded them to Vimeo but unfortunatley, you are just able to upload 1 HD video per week in your free account. I hade fife … sucks!</p>

<p>You can also export the screencasts .mov files. I decided to do so and convert them. Good old <a href="https://www.ffmpeg.org/">ffmpeg</a> time - ding dong! The resulting files from Voila for my 4 Minute screencast is 139 MB. What I want is to share the video in a simple website like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Video Test&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;video controls style="width:700px"&gt;
    &lt;source src="Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;
    &lt;source src="Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen.webm" type="video/webm"/&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/body
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I need to convert the .mov file to an .mp4 file. I don’t want to crop or change anything. The commandline looks like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ffmpeg -i Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen.mov Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen.mp4
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>While converting, ffmpeg is using the H.264/MPEG-4 AVC codec. You could also add the parameter</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>-q:a [quality, INTEGER]
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>for audio quality or</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>-q:v [quality, INTEGER]
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>for video quality. I ommited both because I wanted the best result.</p>

<p>The resulting .mp4 file is now 15 MB in size and the quality is still really good. The next step is to convert the .mp4 file into a .webm file. This is a format resulting of Google’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">vp8 codec</a> and this is done with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libvpx</code>. If you don’t have it already compiled into ffmpeg, you can simply reinstall ffmpeg with homebrew like so:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>brew reinstall ffmpeg --with-libvpx
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Find more info about that at <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/Apps/Build/Audio_and_video_delivery/H.264_support_in_Firefox">Mozillas H.264 support in Firefox site at MDN</a> and at <a href="http://www.webmproject.org/">http://www.webmproject.org</a>.</p>

<p>The commandline looks like this:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>ffmpeg -i Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen_2.mp4 -strict -2 Schule-Neugraben-CMS-Bild-einfuegen.webm
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The flag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-strict -2</code> is neccessary, because ffmpeg doesn’t let you convert the file: <em>The encoder ‘vorbis’ is experimental but experimental codecs are not enabled, add ‘-strict -2’ if you want to use it.</em> 
Ok - as you like!</p>

<p>The resulting .webm file is 9.4 MB in size. That’s cool. And now you are able to visit the website shown above. We have two different files for the HTML5 video tag what will support most browsers. And if someone comes with Internet Explorer … well - I personally don’t care.</p>

<p>One note: converting the .mp4 file to .webm takes really long!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><category term="video" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Make a screencast with Voila and convert the resulting .mov file into a .mp4 and .webm file to include them in the HTML5 video tag.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reminder: Ruby private behaves differently</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/reminder-ruby-private-behaves-differently/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reminder: Ruby private behaves differently" /><published>2014-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/reminder-ruby-private-behaves-differently</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/reminder-ruby-private-behaves-differently/"><![CDATA[<p>Assume you have the following dead simple class:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>class Doc

  private

  def say
    "andy"
  end
end
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We agree, that the method <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">say</code> is marked private and cannot be called like so:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&gt; doc = Doc.new
&gt; doc.say
NoMethodError: private method `say` called for #&lt;Doc:0x007f8c93087c18&gt;
from (irb):22
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Ok. But you already know, that this does not mean, that you can’t access <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">say</code> from outside right? No? Here is the prove:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&gt; doc = Doc.new
&gt; doc.send(:say)
=&gt; "andy" 
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Oh!</p>

<p>I assume you have learned, that you can’t access private methods from a child class. That’s true for many programming languages. But not in Ruby. See this example:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>class TextDoc &lt; Doc
  def spoken_words
    say
  end
end
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>So we want to call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">say</code>, what is declared <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">private</code> in the class <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Doc</code> in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">spoken_words</code>. Does this work?</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&gt; text_doc = TextDoc.new
&gt; text_doc.spoken_words
=&gt; "andy"
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Oh! Wait. WTF?</p>

<p>The point in Ruby is, that the language does not prevent you from doing things if you really want to. It is your responsibility to deal with it - not the language implementors. Having these possibilities opens a lot of doors not only in Ruby’s meta-programming power, but helps also to write less and most importantly readable code. Visibility issues? It’s your responsibility as a developer to take care of.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><category term="ruby" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reminder: Ruby private behaves differently]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fight Internet Slowdown</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/fight-internet-slowdown/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fight Internet Slowdown" /><published>2014-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/fight-internet-slowdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/fight-internet-slowdown/"><![CDATA[<p>As you have entered my blog, you may have noticed an annoying loading icon. US Internet providers want to slow down internet connections for profit. We have to fight against that and keep the Internet free and neutral.</p>

<p>Check out more infos at <a href="https://www.battleforthenet.com/sept10th">https://www.battleforthenet.com/sept10th</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.andy-wenk.de/assets/img/internet-slowdown.png" alt="Internet Slowdown" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As you have entered my blog, you may have noticed an annoying loading icon. US Internet providers want to slow down internet connections for profit. We have to fight against that and keep the Internet free and neutral.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Duke Skelington R.I.P</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/duke-skelington-rip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Duke Skelington R.I.P" /><published>2014-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/duke-skelington-rip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/duke-skelington-rip/"><![CDATA[<p><em>You may say, that’s the nature of things</em></p>

<p>  … but it hurts all the same</p>

<p><em>You may say, you did your best to avoid pain</em></p>

<p>  … but it hurts all the same</p>

<p><em>You knew that the day will come where you need to be strong</em></p>

<p>  … but it hurts all the same</p>

<p><em>You might say, “it’s just a cat in the end”</em></p>

<p>  … but you are wrong</p>

<p><em>He was my friend!</em></p>

<p><em>He was my family!</em></p>

<p><em>He was my hero!</em></p>

<p><img src="https://www.andy-wenk.de/assets/img/duke.png" alt="Duke Skelington" /></p>

<p><strong>R.I.P Duke Skelington - I miss you!</strong></p>

<p>∗ 25.05.2000 - † 11.08.2014</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You may say, that’s the nature of things]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learnings from ‘Object Oriented Design in Ruby’ by Sandi Metz - Part I</title><link href="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/learnings-from-object-oriented-design-in-ruby-by-sandi-metz-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learnings from ‘Object Oriented Design in Ruby’ by Sandi Metz - Part I" /><published>2014-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/learnings-from-object-oriented-design-in-ruby-by-sandi-metz-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.andy-wenk.de/blog/2014/learnings-from-object-oriented-design-in-ruby-by-sandi-metz-part-1/"><![CDATA[<p>During my holidays in Finisterre (or the more correct name Fisterra in Gailego) in the most western part of Spain, and after having finished several greate Scify books by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/#">James S.A. Corey</a> (‘The Expanse’ series), I started to read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/#"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Practical Object-Oriented Programming Design in Ruby</code></a> by Sandi Metz again. This is the first post of some posts I plan to write. The posts will provide a look at the practices Sandi is covering in her great book. The intention of this writing is to intorduce the most basic ideas behind good software design and serve as guidelines you should follow.</p>

<p>In the last two years I was able to identify some of the Ruby-People in the community every Ruby-Programmer should listen to. Among various others, there is <a href="http://">Avid Grim</a> with his great writings, <a href="http://">Justin Weiss</a> with his great blog and <a href="http://">Brandon Hilkert</a> with a great book about how to build Rubygems and a great blog also. Sandi belongs definitely in this club of great Rubyists and I encourge you to follow thes fine people.</p>

<p>In the first part of the posts we are going to have a look at the basics of Object-Oriented Design.</p>

<p>##Introduction</p>

<p>##Object-Orient Design</p>

<p>Sandi writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Object-oriented design is about <em>managing dependencies</em>. It is a set of coding techniques that arrange dependencies such that objects can tolerate change.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Everything is about to change. When we start a software project, we never know which requirements are coming along the way. That means we have to try to avoid heavy dependencies between classes and methods. We should always expect the need for a change in our code. But because we don’t know which part of our code is going to need a change, we need to write code that is changeable.</p>

<p>Change in requirements is the reason why we should not fall into the trap of thinking, that it’s ok to have <em>some</em> dependencies in our <em>small</em> application. Sandi knows why:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The problem with poorly designed <em>small</em> applications is that if they are successfull they grow up to be poorly designed <em>big</em> applications.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I am 100% sure everyone fell into the snake pit where this sentence was true. So we can conclude that it is highly recommended to write well designed applications. It is not easy to achieve this goal. It need’s us to practice a lot because:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Design is thus an art, the art of arranging code.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>##Tools</p>

<p>What are the tools available helping us achieving the goal of good object-oriented design? We are not lost and we do not have to reinvent the wheel. Here is a list of some well known and broadly used principles of object-oriented design.</p>

<p>###<a href="http://">SOLID</a></p>

<p><em>SOLID</em> stands for five principles originally defined by <a href="http://">Michael Feathers</a> and broadcasted by <a href="http://">Uncle Bob Martin</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Single Responsibility</em>:
each method or class has exactly one responsibility and nothing more</li>
  <li><em>Open-Closed</em>:
tbc</li>
  <li><em>Liskov Substitution</em>:
tbc</li>
  <li><em>Interface Segregation</em>:
tbc</li>
  <li><em>Dependency Inversion</em>:
tbc</li>
</ul>

<p>###<a href="http://">DRY</a></p>

<p><em>DRY</em> stands for <em>Don’t Repeat Yourself</em> and it was defined by <a href="http://">Andy Hunt</a> and <a href="http://">Dave Thomas</a>. The idea behind this principle is to avaid duplication in our code. When we recognize duplicated code, we should refactor out the code part to a place (e.g. a method) we can reuse. Doing so, we are able ot remove the duplication.</p>

<p>###<a href="http://">LoD</a></p>

<p><em>LoD</em> stands for <em>Law of Demeter</em> and was defined by the <a href="http://">Demeter project at Northeastern University</a>. tbc</p>

<p>Using these tools will help us improving our code. I can definitely acknowledge this <strong>THESE/AUSSAGE</strong> out of my own experience. And Sandi is seconding this with writing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The principles of good design represent measurable truths and following them improve your code.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>##What is the Design process?</p>

<p>Sandi writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Design is a process of progressive discovery that relies on a feedback loop. This feedback loop should be timely and incremental.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>Feedback Loop</em> is one of the most important tools when creating object-oriented applications. Sandi is mentioning the <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org"><em>iterative techniques of the Agile software movement</em></a>. This is very true but in my opinion even when not following agile practices, we should definitely at least use a feedback loop with the people, we are creating the applicatin for (aka: product owner in agile speak). It is the only way to recognize changes in the requirements and also missunderstandings of requirements. So Sandi states perfectly well, that the feedback loop has to be <em>timely</em> and <em>incremental</em>. Therfore we define the length of one loop (aka: sprint in agile speak). The length depends on the kind of project but the experience showed, that one up to two weeks is fitting very good. The loops are going to be repeated until everybody is satisfied with the results.</p>

<p>##The difference between object-oriented and procedural programming languages</p>

<p>In this section we are having a very quick view to the difference between object-oriented and procedural programming languages.</p>

<p>A procedural language has a fixed set of data types and the syntax of the language is providing operations to work with these data types. We are not able to create new operations or create new data types. But we are able to create <em>functions</em> or <em>methods</em> where we can group together functionality to work on our data to create behaviour. Still, <em>data</em> and <em>behaviour</em> are two complete different things.</p>

<p>In object-oriented languages, <em>data</em> and <em>behaviour</em> are packed into one thing: an <em>object</em>. The operations we can use on a specific object (like String) are <em>‘built into the object itself instead of into the syntax of the language’</em>. Each object contains it’s own <em>data</em> but the <em>behaviour</em> of similar objects is always the same. Because of this reason, <em>‘every object decides for itself how much, or how little, of its data to expose’</em>.</p>

<p>A class-based object-oriented language like Ruby has builtin classes for every data type we expect as programmers. These data types are overlapping with the ones provided by procedural languages like <em>String</em>, <em>Fixnum</em> among others. All these classes are based on the class <em>Class</em>. This brings the ability to create new data-type classes based on <em>Class</em>. We are not limited to the builtin data-ytpes provided by procedural languages. This is a big advantage (among others) of object-oriented languages and most likely the reason why we want to use them.</p>

<p>Even though there are the outlined advantages of object-oriented programming languages, we should definitely not forget the many usecases where we don’t want to use OO languages but languages like <em>C</em> or <em>Erlang</em>.</p>

<p>##Summary</p>

<p>The topic of this first post in the series we had a look to Object-Orient Design. tbc</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><category term="ruby" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learnings from 'Object Oriented Design in Ruby' by Sandi Metz - Part I]]></summary></entry></feed>