<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://virajm.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://virajm.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-06-30T11:47:48-05:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>PhD Student at the Robotics Institute at Carnegie Mellon University working at the intersection of machine learning and plasma control for nuclear fusion.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Spinlaunch with Basic Physics</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2021/spinlaunch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spinlaunch with Basic Physics" /><published>2021-11-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2021/spinlaunch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2021/spinlaunch/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A quick derivation of how a spinlauncher would have to work to get a rocket to space.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Representational Aspects of Depth and Conditioning in Normalizing Flows</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2020/flows/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representational Aspects of Depth and Conditioning in Normalizing Flows" /><published>2020-12-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2020/flows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2020/flows/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I authored a post on the CMU ML blog explaining recent work that characterizes what kinds of functions can be represented by normalizing flows.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Austin Travel Guide</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2018/travel.guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Austin Travel Guide" /><published>2018-05-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2018/travel.guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2018/travel.guide/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Myself, Connor Gunn, and a few other friends wrote a travel guide to our hometown of Austin, TX. It's here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Backlash</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2017/backlash/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Backlash" /><published>2017-02-23T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2017/backlash</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2017/backlash/"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I was on Jeopardy! and accidentally flipped off Alex Trebek and the American viewing public. I’d like to write about the experience of being nationally infamous.</p>

<p>First, there’s an important and meaningful disclaimer I feel compelled to say. Jeopardy! was an amazing experience and everyone there was lovely and Alex Trebek is a boss and the other competitors are fantastic people.</p>

<p>After we taped the episode, Mari (another contestant) asked me if I meant to do it. I’m not smart enough to think about Jeopardy strategy, talk about differential geometry, and connive to make a rude gesture at the viewing public and a national icon. I was oblivious, and I promptly forgot about it.</p>

<p>When Jeopardy tweeted a video of my contestant interview the day it aired, I was reminded. And it was hilarious. In the Internet age, the thing to do in this situation is make gifs and memes, so we complied. That was as far as I thought it was going to go.</p>

<p>Later that day, my brother sent me a link to a BroBible article about it. And then UpRoxx, the Huffington Post, the Daily Mail, E! News, etc. It’s worth noting here that of all these news organizations, only a single freelance writer reached out for comment. Twitter was aflame and Instagram lit up. Some of these articles jokingly conjectured that I had won a bet or that my finger cramped. All of this was fairly entertaining and I certainly relished the attention.</p>

<p>But the fun ended fairly quickly. Public life in America has a dark side and I’d like to give you a taste of it.</p>

<p>It started with simple disrespect in the vein of “You are a moron and a disgusting example of children not taught respect. Ashamed that you are from Texas.”</p>

<p>And</p>

<p>“Spoiled little rich boy! The poster child of arrogant millenials that thinks he’s so cool he can make obscene jestures in public, probably on a dare from another spoiled child. We don’t need your type. Go back. You’re here just to take advantage, not contribute.”</p>

<p>But as the last one started hinting, the messages quickly went from vaguely insulting to specifically racist.</p>

<p>“Where were you born?” was a subtle one.</p>

<p>“You are a disgusting example of education in 2017. Go back India and worship cows.”[sic] was not.</p>

<p>“Stupid fucking muslim. Don’t disrespect Americans.” was a bit off base.</p>

<p>The single word “ISIS” was concerning as well.</p>

<p>But “you may have given alex and the viewers ‘the finger’ but those two asians you played against gave you ‘the boot’. you got your ass whipped bad. i always thought asians were smarter than indians (i think that’s what you are) and you proved it in your last two jeopardy games. the country did notice you wearing the same shirt under your college sweatshirt for your three appearances. now we can safely say that you and your shirt stink!!! was that an hawaiian or indian shirt? you have set stanford admissions back greatly with your appearance. not a fan of yours!!!</p>

<p>signed, an almost as stupid as you caucasian guy.”</p>

<p>took the cake, if the cake was made of cardboard and frosted with shit with the words “FUCK BROWN PEOPLE” written in lighter shit frosting on the top of this shitty cake.</p>

<p>Also somebody called me “trailer trash,” which was confusing.</p>

<p>I have a few thoughts about all this. Race in America is a confusing topic and certainly not something I have always handled well.</p>

<p>First, I’m surprised by how inconsistent the messages were. Some people thought I was a Muslim and that by itself is a dirty word for much of America. Others knew that India and the Muslim Middle East are different places. I have no real explanation for “Trailer trash.”</p>

<p>The optimistic view is that racism is predominantly a fear of people who are different. The fact that these people felt the need to find me on the internet and hurl slurs at me without any real understanding of who I am or what race I am makes me hope that if someone told them what race I am and why it’s pretty chill and that all I really want is a steady supply of Mexican food and to spend time with people I love and do work—then they’d stop hating.</p>

<p>But there’s also the issue of what happened the next day in Olathe, Kansas. Two Indian software engineers watching basketball at a bar were shot without provocation after being told to “Get out of my country.” I love bars and I love basketball and I’ve worked as a software engineer.</p>

<p>I was also born in Ohio and raised in West Virginia and Texas. I have a Texas flag on my ceiling. It seems inconceivable to me that I could go to ‘my country’ and it not be this one.</p>

<p>To be honest, I’ve elided the question of my own race and its meaning for my entire life. Growing up the son of wealthy parents in predominantly wealthy neighborhoods usually tends (not always) to insulate you from these kind of problems to the point where the only racially motivated question on my mind was whether White girls would like me.</p>

<p>And I think Indians in general don’t ask these types of questions too often. We all know that there are hidden prejudices and biases, but in my experience the primary reaction is to keep our heads down and work harder. This needs to change.</p>

<p>Of course, there’s an elephant in the room here. Since the election of Donald Trump it has once again gotten easier to see America as a nation of White people with interloping people of color. There’s no Black president to point to. There’s preferential treatment for getting Christians out of the Middle East. There might soon be a wall to the south to keep out the brown folks down there.</p>

<p>A nation with a Statue of Liberty in its greatest city and a wall on its southern border is a conflicted one where stuff like what happened in Olathe will continue. I’d like to end on a happy note. But I don’t have anything super positive to say about this. Even though Jeopardy! was a dream come true for me and I’ll cherish it for the rest of my life, even though today I cashed a check for $25k, and even though I got my fifteen minutes, I’ll also remember Olathe and my inbox.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I won $25k on Jeopardy! But there were consequences.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Open Door Policy</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2016/open-door/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Open Door Policy" /><published>2016-05-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-05-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2016/open-door</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2016/open-door/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a lot going on at Stanford right now. Election petitions are in season, we’re getting a new president, and everyone is once again realizing that dead week is a myth.</p>

<p>Normally, I would block out all the news and focus on that sunny day in Texas two weeks from now when my puppy realizes I haven’t moved to Siberia and can take him for walks and feed him tacos again.</p>

<p>But today, I found that something I hold dear has been threatened: Stanford’s open door policy.</p>

<p>I’m going to be an RA next year. In a four-class dorm, I’m going to have to deal with a potential hard liquor ban in the most uncomfortable way. There will be freshmen on my floor. But I’ll get to that.</p>

<p>One problem is that there will be people on my floor who are over 21: people who can go out to the Dutch Goose and order an Old Fashioned right this instant.</p>

<p>Who am I, a nineteen-year-old who doesn’t have that privilege, to tell them what to do?</p>

<p>Who am I, someone who has not one but two (sorry, mom) bottles of Wild Turkey on my shelf, to, six months from now, tell someone that they can’t do just that?</p>

<p>Who am I, someone who made more than my share of mistakes as a freshman, to restrict my freshmen to the point that they can’t try those things out for themselves?</p>

<p>I didn’t sign up to be a policeman. The whole extended adventure of the staff selection process was joyful to me because, at Stanford, being an RA is not about being a policeman. I want to be a teacher and a builder of communities. I want to help my residents when they need it and celebrate with them when they don’t. I want my residents and especially my freshmen to revel in the fact that they chose a school that treats them as adults who can make adult decisions, and acknowledges that sometimes they fail.</p>

<p>You might respect the police. You might follow the rules of the police. But when you feel homesick and you’re having romantic problems and you’ve gained 10 lbs and your friends here aren’t quite like your friends at home — are you going to vent all that to the police? By making RAs into policemen, we are necessarily hurting the staff’s ability to help students with everything other than drinking.</p>

<p>In real life, we can justify these harms because the police aren’t therapists and they keep us safe.</p>

<p>But I believe that this plan doesn’t. Banning vodka doesn’t lead to less vodka; it leads to vodka hidden in a closet that is chugged behind a closed door. It leads to a tiny freshman girl puking up vodka or passing out behind a closed door and a group of bewildered freshmen afraid to ask for help because they might all get in trouble for having liquor in the first place.</p>

<p>And all of a sudden, having hard alcohol is just as cool as it was in 10th grade for some folks. I may be a miscreant, but banning something is the easiest way to make me do it. Perhaps some freshmen are as foolish as I am.</p>

<p>The RAs-as-policemen approach actually makes our freshmen less safe.</p>

<p>So since I, and probably many other staff, don’t believe that banning liquor solves problems of safety and actively will damage our relationship as mentors with the residents, the policy is not likely to be effectively enforced.</p>

<p>“But Stanford would never try and stop something from happening that will happen anyway”, you might exclaim. But the two weeks I spent vaguely sick in October would prove you wrong. I don’t think Full Moon is going to end if the administrators turn off the lights and stop serving mouthwash as hors-d’oeuvres. I’ll be there. And now that I’ve announced that, so will many of you.</p>

<p>Just as some students will gather under the full moon in the quad next October, many staff would rather teach than police. I believe that the open door policy is not only the best way forward, but also reflects the high expectations and commensurate trust placed in Stanford students. Why, then, would the administration loudly propose changes that undermine our core values?</p>

<p>I defer to you, Mr. Boardman, Provost Etchemendy, and President Hennessy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stanford tried to ban alcohol for freshmen. I disagree from the RA perspective.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Have you ever…</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2016/have-you-ever/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have you ever…" /><published>2016-02-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-02-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2016/have-you-ever</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2016/have-you-ever/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever Facetimed your dog? He hears your voice and runs around and barks and then lies down and you call his name and he sees you on this shiny chunk of not-food, but he licks it anyway, plaintively mourning the not-presence of the guy who’s sometimes around who is the only one who knows how to fit the harness properly to take him on a walk.</p>

<p>It’s heartbreaking.</p>

<p>How do you think your dog would deal with Snapchat?</p>

<p>Have you ever eaten a microwave burrito but the microwave was clearly loafing and the gooey middle was not so gooey? So you consider going out to eat but it’s Valentine’s day and you don’t want to deal with that at any restaurant so you end up ordering pizza and the delivery guy locks eyes with you and you both know that neither of you is exactly having a blast. And you wonder if he needs a friend like you do. What if he likes Smash Bros too? Or The Office? Anything is better than the look of quasi-desperation in his eyes as the door closes and you begin to shamefully eat your pizza.</p>

<p>It’s only 5 slices later that you realize you didn’t tip him.</p>

<p>Have you ever been in one of those lines? You know the ones. Where you aren’t really that invested in what you’re waiting for but you’ve sunk too much time in to give up and your mind begins to wander and the people adjacent look grumpy and the DMV or post office or whatever smells just faintly of dry rot and there’s a faint buzz from a light fixture about to die? But have you been in one of those lines without anything to keep your attention from wandering? Not anymore.</p>

<p>We are never ever bored anymore. There’s always a snapchat story or article or FaceTaGramTer or whatever. There’s this bit in a book I read (that recently turned 20) where there’s a film that’s so entertaining it was dangerous. Like they tested it by telling a research subject to cut off a digit to watch it again. I wonder if the collective Internet cellphone social startup business isn’t converging to that. Maybe the comprehensive use of technology is making the little annoyances of life just comfortable enough that we won’t deal with them. I know that’s straight out of Huxley, but Huxley probably didn’t come up with it while being encouraged to water his plants by a mediocre rap producer.</p>

<p>I’m not saying this because of any holier-than-thou impulse that I know more about the world than anyone else around. People who see a lot of me know that that’s clearly untrue. I’m also not saying this because I hate technology or anything like that. I’m probably going to work on it for the rest of my life.</p>

<p>I’m writing this as a way to justify going on walks to places without my cell phone and maybe even learning to cook. And so that maybe I’m a hypocrite if I don’t at least try.</p>

<p>Have you ever opened up your phone and moved the screen around, read some shit, fiddled with some doodads, and closed it? And then realized you have no idea what the hell you just did and read?</p>

<p>I don’t have the answer to this, but I felt like it needed to be written down. It’s the hidden ailment of our time.</p>

<p>I hope you read this while pooping. It sure beats the alternative.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A pile of writing, mostly to get out stuff in my head at the time.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taco Bell and Other Adventures</title><link href="https://virajm.com/blog/2015/taco-bell/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taco Bell and Other Adventures" /><published>2015-10-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-10-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://virajm.com/blog/2015/taco-bell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://virajm.com/blog/2015/taco-bell/"><![CDATA[<p>Hi!</p>

<p>My name’s Viraj Mehta and the only place I could think to start was Taco Bell.</p>

<p>To be perfectly clear, I don’t think Taco Bell is good food, either nutritionally or in taste. But I have noticed that Taco Bell succeeds more than any other restaurant at being there for me when I need it most. As a vegetarian who has spent a fairly large fraction of his life road-tripping around the Lower 48, Taco Bell is my go-to for when I’m in Lubbock, TX or Sandusky, OH, or, on one memorable occasion, Gary, IN. The familiar blend of rehydrated beans, bland tortillas, and cheese that is almost Kraft but not quite is the same anywhere you go. So while I have never had a good meal at Taco Bell, I’ve also never had a bad one.</p>

<p>This unyielding devotion to consistency has bought Taco Bell a favored place in the hearts, minds, and stomachs of my family. Whenever we get together, wherever we get together, after an excellent home-cooked Indian meal for dinner, the cousins pile into the car and roll out to the Bell. It’s a weird and definitely unhealthy tradition, but it ties us together in the most second-generation immigrant of ways: Taco Bell is something this country generally laughs at that we have taken to love. Love for its consistency and love for its availability.</p>

<p>The first-generation equivalent is way weirder.</p>

<p>My dad is a 59-year-old gastroenterologist who has been in this country for over 25 years, but he has a few things he likes here more than usual: He likes basketball. He likes pizza. He likes mustard. Guessing at the experiences that have led to this oddly specific collection of favorites is a thought experiment I think might be enjoyable for the reader. The first is easy.</p>

<p>It helps to picture my father: a skinny Indian man with a thick black mustache and a relationship with grammar that can best be described as casual.</p>

<p>For a man who made it here in the eighties and grew up playing badminton and cricket, the grace and power and, ultimately, dominance of Magic and Larry in the 80s and Michael in the 90s must have made lonely nights after long hospital shifts that much more bearable. To me, the image of a lonely Indian man in a new country dazzled by the NBA evokes pride in this nation and my ancestry. For a guy in Chicago who dealt with human misery all day, this had to have been an escape.</p>

<p>Then and now, my dad generally eats one meal a day. Back then, it was two Dominos large cheese pizzas. Bachelor to the max. This happened every day for two years in the early nineties. While he was watching the ascendancy of Jordan, my dad was eating cheese pizza and chilling out.</p>

<p>I’m sure he wasn’t too familiar with cheese before that. There are times in my life where I’m a little bored or stressed and my mind and body begin to wander and I snap back to reality at the fridge having eaten a couple handfuls of shredded cheese and I wonder what the hell is wrong with me and marvel at how I’m not 400 lbs and experience the sickly-sweet satisfaction that all of this has brought me. My dad didn’t have that lovely cacophony of sensation. He had Dominos. I am spoiled.</p>

<p>I’m not entirely sure how mustard fits into this at all.</p>

<p>It doesn’t go with pizza, and only is really paired with meat-heavy foods. However, for someone to go his entire life without ever tasting it and then tenatively dipping a French Fry into this bright-yellow chutney dolloped on his plate while alone at some McDonalds in the greater Chicago area, mustard would probably have been shocking. Especially, if on this quest to try condiments, he had tried ketchup first.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My heritage through low-end Mexican food.]]></summary></entry></feed>